Mary French Sheldon Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Mary French Sheldon Papers 1885-1938
MSS39677
Sheldon, Mary French, 1847-1936
1,350 items
7 containers plus 1 oversize
2.8 linear feet
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Author, lecturer, and explorer. Correspondence, writings, lectures, notes, clippings, address book, drawings, awards, menus, books, photographs, passports, scrapbooks, and miscellaneous material relating primarily to Belgium, the Belgian Congo, and Africa.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Albert I, King of the Belgians, 1875-1934--Correspondence.; Flaubert, Gustave, 1821-1880. Salammbo.; Sheldon, Mary French, 1847-1936.; Stanley, Henry M. (Henry Morton), 1841-1904--Correspondence.
Places
Africa--Description and travel.; Congo (Democratic Republic)--Description and travel.
Occupations
Authors.; Explorers.; Lecturers.
Provenance
The papers of Mary French Sheldon, author, lecturer, and explorer, were given to the Library of Congress by Sheldon’s estate in 1947.
Transfers
Two nitrate negative motion picture films have been transferred to the Motion Picture, Broadcasting, and Recorded Sound Division where they are identified as part of the Mary French Sheldon Papers.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of Mary French Sheldon are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Mary French Sheldon (1847-1936) span the years 1885-1938. The collection consists of correspondence, writings, lectures, notes, clippings, an address book, drawings, awards, menus, books, photographs, passports, scrapbooks, and miscellaneous material primarily concerning Sheldon’s interest in Africa, particularly the Belgian Congo. Also included is correspondence relating to her travels and lectures; fictional writings; translations of various works, including Salammbo by Gustave Flaubert; an unpublished work relating to the Congo; drawings by Shelton; and photographs of various subjects, especially Africa. Correspondents include Henry Morton Stanley, Albert I, King of the Belgians, and several of Albert's cabinet ministers.
Arrangement of the Papers
This collection is arranged alphabetically by type of material
Container List
- Address book, undated (Box 1)
- Award, 1893 See Oversize (Box 1)
- Calling cards, undated (Box 1)
- Clippings, 1915-1938 (Box 1)
- Correspondence (Box 1)
  - 1885-1922, (9 folders) (Box 1)
  - 1923-1935, undated, (7 folders) (Box 2)
- Drawings, 1915-1926, undated See also Oversize (Box 2)
- Lectures, 1892-1924, undated (Box 2)
- Menus, 1897-1905 (Box 2)
- Miscellany, 1885, 1909, 1926-1927, undated (Box 2)
- Notes, undated (Box 2)
  - Africa (Box 2)
  - Belgium (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 3)
  - Quotations (Box 3)
- Obituary, 1936 (Box 3)
- Passports, 1903-1931 See also Oversize (Box 3)
- Photographs (Box 3)
  - Africa, 1903-1916, undated, (4 folders) (Box 3)
  - Autographed portraits, 1897, 1916-1925, undated See also Oversize (Box 3)
  - Belgian royal family, 1922, undated See also Oversize (Box 3)
  - Louvain, Belgium, 1914, undated (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous, 1921-1930 (Box 4)
  - Sheldon, Mary French, 1903-1907, undated (Box 4)
  - Slides, undated (Box 4)
  - Ward, Herbert, undated (Box 4)
- Scrapbooks, 1896-1936, undated, (2 folders) (Box 4)
- Writings (Box 4)
  - By Sheldon (Box 4)
    - “Congo” (Box 4)
      - Albert I, King of the Belgians, 1909-1923, undated (Box 4)
      - Colonial, 1922-1923, undated (Box 4)
      - Development, 1916, undated (Box 5)
      - Foreword, undated (Box 5)
      - Léopold II, King of the Belgians, 1898, undated (Box 5)
      - Miscellany, 1891-1928, undated (Box 5)
    - Congo tribal customs, undated (Box 5)
    - “The Drifter Anchored,” undated (Box 5)
    - Fragments, undated (Box 5)
    - “How He and She Collaborated,” undated (Box 5)
    - Letter to the editor, 1903 (Box 5)
    - “Love’s Hazard,” undated (Box 5)
    - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 5)
    - Memoirs of Judas, translated by Sheldon, undated (Box 5)
      - Chapters 1-11, (2 folders) (Box 5)
      - Chapters 12-33, (4 folders) (Box 6)
    - “Nature’s Child,” undated (Box 6)
    - Pilate and Ovid’s Daughter, undated (Box 6)
    - Salammbo, translated by Sheldon, 1885-1886, (2 folders) (Box 6)
  - By others (Box 7)
    - Stanley, Henry M., The Congo and the Founding of the Free State, 1885, (2 vols.) (Box 7)
    - Ward, Sarita, A Valiant Gentleman; Being the Biography of Herbert Ward, Artist and Man of Action, 1927 (Box 7)
- Award, 1893 (Container 1) (Box OV 1)
- Drawings, 1915, 1926 (Container 2) (Box OV 1)
- Passports, 1903-1931 (Container 3) (Box OV 1)
- Photographs (Box OV 1)
  - Autographed portraits, 1897 (Container 3) (Box OV 1)
  - Belgian royal family, 1922 (Container 3) (Box OV 1)